<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Empty Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://theempty.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://theempty.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-17T14:08:18-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://theempty.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mohammad El-Abid]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://theempty.github.com/blog/2012/08/17/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-17T13:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://theempty.github.com/blog/2012/08/17/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My name&#8217;s Mohammad El-Abid. I&#8217;ve been working with the web since before I can remember. I love writing about technology, games, and animation. Hopefully this will be a blog of high quality posts updated when I&#8217;m not flooded with school work (<a href="http://bridgeport.edu/">University of Bridgeport</a> 2015) or working with my <a href="http://theempty.github.com/resume">clients</a>.</p>

<h3>Technology</h3>

<p>I currently work as a Ruby on Rails senior developer. But teach in Java, learn C++ at school, use Node.JS for personal projects, C for small/easy utilities, and basic for robotics. I&#8217;ll be talking about issues and patterns I run into and how I fixed the problem. I&#8217;ll probably talk about what I see when I&#8217;m teaching, common mistakes, clever ideas, and such. Every now my technology posts might get blurred with gaming. The <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1523379957/oculus-rift-step-into-the-game">Rift</a> looks amazing.</p>

<h3>Animation</h3>

<p>Thanks to <a href="http://students.autodesk.com">Autodesk&#8217;s educational site</a>, I&#8217;m learning Maya 2013 to replace <a href="http://hash.com/">Animation:Master</a>. I&#8217;m hoping to use my modeling skills to create some basic objects for a game. The game doesn&#8217;t have any specifics, just something I think every programmer wants to do. Game makers are like the rockstars of programmers.</p>

<h3>Games</h3>

<p>I&#8217;ll be playing a bit of <a href="http://guildwars2.com/">Guild Wars 2</a> during school. It will be my first MMORPG. I also play games like Super Meat Boy, DiRT 3 or Showdown, and Tekken. Don&#8217;t expect too much on games or math crunching posts, I&#8217;m not a very good gamer, just someone that enjoys games.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
